<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reviews on mauromorales.com</title>
    <link>http://mauromorales.com/tags/reviews/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reviews on mauromorales.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mauro Morales</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://mauromorales.com/tags/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Review 2014</title>
      <link>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/01/annual-review-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/01/annual-review-2014/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;2014 has been a year I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to forget. During the last five years, I&amp;rsquo;ve
done a list of goals and I&amp;rsquo;ve focused on reaching as many as possible. This year
more important than the amount of reached goals, it&amp;rsquo;s been all about the quality
of the events that happened in my life. So without further do, here is my review
of what happened to be a wonderful year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;READMORE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-good&#34;&gt;The Good&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was given the task to find two programmers to grow our team at LAS.
The first of January we welcomed them in Leysin and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky enough to count
them as part of my family while away from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in Europe has allowed me to watch some of my favorite bands. In January
I was able to see Protest the Hero and TesseracT. Up until now I think I&amp;rsquo;m just
missing A7X to scratch of my favorites list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February I managed to move out to a bigger apartment. Living in a studio was
becoming a pain in the butt so that was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting to learn how to snowboard. I&amp;rsquo;m not really into extreme
sports, ok who am I kidding? I&amp;rsquo;m not really into sports so having done that made
me feel really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March was the climax of my year. Gretel and I were able to celebrate a small
civil wedding only with our close family which was very special for me and for
the religious wedding we had a huge party. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s because of the fact that
it was my own wedding that I cannot be objective but I really think it was one
of the must fun and cool weddings ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the honey moon we went to Brazil. Rio and São Paulo are great, the
Brazilian culture left me a good taste of mouth and I&amp;rsquo;d love to dedicate more
time to it in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the middle of the year I went to RuLu, a Ruby conference in Lyon. Gretel came
with me so we were able to learn about a very pretty city and enjoy all the
delicious French food. We ended up finding out Lyon is considered the
gastronomic capital, yum!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something really interesting this year was to have multiple companies interested
in my profile. I got two offers to work in different cities in Switzerland
including Zurich and three cities in Germany including Berlin. Not bad for the
Guatemalan average Joe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close with a flourish I visited the city of love with my wife. Despite the
bad weather, we got to know places, eat and fall in love even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bad&#34;&gt;The Bad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having spent another six months away from Gretel was the hardest thing of the
year. We were not planning for this which made it harder than last year. The
good thing was that in October we closed that chapter from our lives and now we
can start to build our home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the negative things that happened were caused by my lack of
motivation during the year. I didn&amp;rsquo;t exercise much, I didn&amp;rsquo;t read as much as
I normally do and I didn&amp;rsquo;t work on side projects. The direct results were that
I gained some weight, I didn&amp;rsquo;t learn as much as I wanted to and I didn&amp;rsquo;t launch
my first product. The good thing is that those will be the specific areas I will
be focusing on in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goals based system has proven to work and I already have one for 2015.
However I realize I need to have a framework based on habits in order to keep
hustling even when I&amp;rsquo;m not in my best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all I can say that I&amp;rsquo;m very satisfied and I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to start the
year full of energy. Happy new year! I hope you can accomplish all your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>