<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Women In Tech on mauromorales.com</title>
    <link>http://mauromorales.com/tags/women-in-tech/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Women In Tech on mauromorales.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mauro Morales</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://mauromorales.com/tags/women-in-tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Ally Skills Workshop Review</title>
      <link>http://mauromorales.com/2015/10/08/ally-skills-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mauromorales.com/2015/10/08/ally-skills-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the chance to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://adainitiative.org/continue-our-work/workshops-and-training/&#34;&gt;Ally Skills
Workshop&lt;/a&gt;
with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/vaurorapub&#34;&gt;Valerie Aurora&lt;/a&gt; and can&amp;rsquo;t recommend it
enough. This was an enlightening experience on learning how to support women in
their workplaces and communities and it should be given at every tech event or
better yet be part of the training in tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;READMORE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valerie is a very cool person. She presented herself very modestly but after
reading more about her I think she could have bragged much more about her
development skills. She gave a 30 minute introduction on the class and put us in
groups so we could work on multiple scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each scenario was about real life encounters that women have had at their
workplaces and made them feel uncomfortable. We as men got the chance to express
how we think we should deal with the situation in order to give our support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also women in our groups which made everything more realistic because
they could give us immediate feedback and share similar experiences. Once we
were done we would share back with Valerie and she would give us additional
feedback or correct us when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt happier and more productive when working in teams were people
respect one another and I believe this kind of workshop provides the necessary
tools and hands on experience to build such environments for women.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>