<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ledger on mauromorales.com</title>
    <link>http://mauromorales.com/tags/ledger/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ledger on mauromorales.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mauro Morales</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://mauromorales.com/tags/ledger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Ledger Tutorial part 1</title>
      <link>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/15/ledger-tutorial-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/15/ledger-tutorial-part-1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ledger-cli.org/&#34;&gt;Ledger&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool to keep track of your
finances. It&amp;rsquo;s simple, fast and most important it doesn&amp;rsquo;t limit you like most
other tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following post is a small introduction on how to start traking your finances
this 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;READMORE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing ledger in OS X is as simple as calling a brew command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;brew install ledger
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ledger-cli.org/download.html&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find information for
other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;define-a-starting-point&#34;&gt;Define a starting point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep track of your finances you need to start somewhere. If you are
doing this at the beginning of the year or in the middle of it, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
matter. The important thing is that you have the sources of your different
accounts and credit cards so you can migrate them to ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will suggest you try with your current balance today. Don&amp;rsquo;t try to get old
data now. Picking up a new tool is already hard work, specially if you need to
build a habit to use it. Plus once you dominate it you will be able to automate
things and you might be able to import that data in a snap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point for this tutorial will be January 1st 2015. So now I go into
every imaginary account I have and verify what is my balance up to that day.
Once I have collected all that information I will write it down into my journal
file from which ledger will read and generate reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a file called journal.dat and add the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;; Testing ledger CLI
2015/01/01  Opening Balance
  Assets:BankOne:Checking                $100.00
  Assets:BankTwo:Savings               $2,000.00
  Liabilities:BankOne:Mastercard        $-250.00
  Liabilities:BankThree:Visa             $-30.00
  Equity:Opening Balances
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 1:&lt;/strong&gt; starts with a semicolon and it&amp;rsquo;s just a comment so you don&amp;rsquo;t really need
it but it&amp;rsquo;s very useful when you need to keep notes about a particular expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You will find other ways to put comments in the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ledger-cli.org/docs.html&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;. Feel free to use the one
you prefer. For consistency purposes I will use the semicolon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 2:&lt;/strong&gt; starts with a date. This is the date from the registry we are adding.
&lt;em&gt;Everything between this date and the next empty line will be our registry.&lt;/em&gt; The
format is &lt;strong&gt;YYYY/MM/DD&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Banks don&amp;rsquo;t always follow the same format for dates
so be careful with this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the date we see the payee. This is the entity to whom the transaction is
being referenced. If you bought something from Amazon.com here you would put
&amp;ldquo;Amazon&amp;rdquo;. Was the case that your employer paid your salary, here you would write
your employer&amp;rsquo;s name. In this case we will call it &amp;ldquo;Opening Balance&amp;rdquo; since there
is no real entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lines 3-4:&lt;/strong&gt; Correspond to assets. In this case we have two banks. One with
a Checking account and one with a Savings account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 5-6:&lt;/strong&gt; Represents liabilites, a Mastercard from the same bank
than our Checkings account and a Visa from another bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 7:&lt;/strong&gt; is the last line of the registry. You can see that it has no value
assigned to it. When you do this, Ledger knows that you expect him to add
everything in the previous lines and balance it to the given account. In this
case our account is &amp;ldquo;Equity:Openin Balances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This special account is necesary because Ledger is a double-entry accounting
system. That means that for every transaction there has to be a transaction of
equal negative value so that everything balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;knowing-your-net-worth&#34;&gt;Knowing your Net Worth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfect now that we have written down all the values of our accounts down.
Run in the terminal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;ledger -f journal.dat balance Assets Liabilities
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this command says is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ledger from the file journal.dat balance my Assets and Liabilities. The result
will be as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;           $2,100.00  Assets
             $100.00    BankOne:Checking
           $2,000.00    BankTwo:Savings
            $-280.00  Liabilities
            $-250.00    BankOne:Mastercard
             $-30.00    BankThree:Visa
--------------------
           $1,820.00
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 1:&lt;/strong&gt; is the total of your Assets. &lt;em&gt;The sum of BankOne:Checking
and BankTwo:Savings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 4:&lt;/strong&gt; is the total of your Liabilities. &lt;em&gt;The sum of BankOne:Mastercard and
BankThree:Visa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 8:&lt;/strong&gt; is your net worth. &lt;em&gt;The sum of your Assets and your Liabilities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this information now you know that even if you see $2,100.00 in your banks
that you actually only have $1,820.00 that are yours because you have $280 in
credit that you need to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you liked this post please let me know in the comments so I write more about
this topic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacking your finances</title>
      <link>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/08/hacking-your-finances/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mauromorales.com/2015/01/08/hacking-your-finances/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Being a good developer is not only about knowing how to code. There are many
other skills like communication, management, decision-making, etc. One of those
very important skills is keeping track of your personal finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;READMORE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-you-begin&#34;&gt;Before you begin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two important things to learn if you want to keep your finances under
control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a tool that makes it &lt;strong&gt;EASY&lt;/strong&gt; to keep track of your income and expenses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to develop the &lt;strong&gt;HABIT&lt;/strong&gt; of using that tool constantly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to generate the right reports in order to make &lt;strong&gt;SMART&lt;/strong&gt; decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-the-right-tool&#34;&gt;Finding the right tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the right tool is the easy part. All you need to do is to find something
that &lt;strong&gt;a)&lt;/strong&gt; covers all your requirements and &lt;strong&gt;b)&lt;/strong&gt; makes you feel comfortable when
using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By covering all your requirements what I mean is that the tool must be able to
adapt to the kind of finances you manage. This will be very specific to each
individual so you will have to find out what you need but here is a list of the
important things I require from my tool&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connect or import my non US bank statements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;handle multiple currencies including Guatemalan Quetzales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access it while traveling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be able to track virtual accounts within my accounts (ie: funds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track reimbursements from multiple companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;present reports of net flow, monthly expenses, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;track budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now don&amp;rsquo;t think that I came to have all these needs since I started keeping
track of my finances. The first tool I used was Microsoft Money, it did all
I needed and I could make reports easily. Later on I switched to using Google
Sheets since it was so easy to access it from any computer and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t using
Windows any more. After that I tried GNUCash because it did all that my
spreadsheet did and more, plus thanks to Dropbox I could have it updated in
every machine I used. My last and current tool is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ledger-cli.org/&#34;&gt;Ledger&lt;/a&gt; because it allows me to stay withing the
confines of the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the fact that you have to use a tool that you enjoy using.
The truth is I will always prefer to use a tool over the command line than over
the GUI because it makes me feel more productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;developing-a-habit&#34;&gt;Developing a Habit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a habit is more complicated and this is why your tool has to make it
easy for you because habits are more likely to stick if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like
a pain doing them. This is why you want to automate as much as you can of the
process and then make a routine about the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tools like mint that can make pretty much everything for you but if
you care about privacy I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend it. In my case I don&amp;rsquo;t use it
because they limit usage only to their list of associated banks. Being a CLI
tool, Ledger is fully automatable but be warned that this might take a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially you might want to do all the process by hand because this will allow
you to see which are the painful parts in the process and also will make you
feel more comfortable with the tool. Doing the process manually also allows you
to build the rules on which your automation will be based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how many transactions you make every month you can do your finances
every day/week/two weeks/month. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend doing them less than every
month and more than once a day would be definitely too much. For me biweekly is
the best option. I do it once every 5th of the month because it is when I have
to pay my cards and I do it once every 20th because it is when I get paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the trick to create a routine is &lt;strong&gt;1)&lt;/strong&gt; having a trigger &lt;strong&gt;2)&lt;/strong&gt; doing the process
without interruptions &lt;strong&gt;3)&lt;/strong&gt; having a reward. This is why I chose those specific
dates because there are specific triggers and rewards as you can see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5th&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;20th&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trigger&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Credit Card payment due&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I get paid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Process&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pay Credit Cards &amp;amp; update ledger&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Update ledger &amp;amp; generate Reports&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reward&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t pay interests&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m confident on where I stand&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another little hack I have is that I use the card for everything. If I take cash
out I keep it as a miscellaneous expense and I don&amp;rsquo;t record any detail of it. Some
people like to use their smart-phone to keep track of those expenses but I find
it tedious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have defined your habit you just have to stick to it. No matter what,
you stick to it! Believe me after a while it will become habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;generating-the-right-reports&#34;&gt;Generating the right reports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kind of decisions you need to make will depend on your current financial
situation. Whether you should spend some money or not will be completely
different if you are in debt or not. So first you need to determine what are
your priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know your priorities you need to create a budget. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to go
through that right now but I will in a future post. Creating a budget is like
setting up your Key Performance Indicators. If you stick to it you will reach
your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you know you need to replace your computer every 3 years and you are
willing to spend no more than $2000 on it. Then you know you need to put $55
aside each month in order to accomplish your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reports you may want to have and with enough data to play with
you may even come up with new ones but I believe having the following three is
a good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Net Worth:&lt;/strong&gt; You want to know how much money do you have and how much you
owe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monthly Expenses:&lt;/strong&gt; You want to know where your money is going.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funds Balance:&lt;/strong&gt; You want to measure where you stand with your goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping track of your finances is not harder than coding or managing a project.
If you gamify it you may even have lot&amp;rsquo;s of fun while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working on a couple of posts in order to show in detail how I use Ledger. In
the mean time feel free to contact me with any questions you may have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>